Guide to the Samuel Blachley Webb papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Blachley Webb papers
1756-1819
MS 539
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.5
(15 boxes)
The Webb papers consist of letterbooks, correspondence, journals, notebooks, orderly books, papers, and military records documenting the personal life and military career of Samuel Blachley Webb, who served in the American Revolutionary forces under Israel Putnam and George Washington. Notable correspondents include: Joseph Barrell, Silas Deane, Nathanael Greene, Alexander Hamilton, Robert Morris, Samuel Otis, Timothy Pickering, Jonathan Trumbull, George Washington, and Catharine Hogeboom Webb.
Webb, Samuel Blachley, 1753-1807
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Webb Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mrs. William Seward Webb, Col. G. Creighton Webb, F. Egerton Webb, and the children of General Alexander Stewart Webb in 1936. The papers were originally given as The Webb Papers. They have been divided into three collections: The Samuel Blachley Webb Papers, The Alexander Stewart Webb Papers. The James Watson Webb Papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected correspondence is published in Family Letters of Samuel Blachley Webb (1912).
Selected correspondence and journals are published in Correspondence and Journals of Samuel Blachley Webb (1893-1894), 3 vols.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Blachley Webb was born in Wethersfield, Connecticut on December 15, 1753. His mother later married Silas Deane, whom Webb served as private secretary. In 1775 Webb was appointed aide to General Israel Putnam and in 1776 was made aide-de-camp to General George Washington, with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. He wrote the order making public the Declaration of Independence, was a prisoner of the British for three years (1777-1781), served as grand marshall at Washington's inauguration, and was a merchant from 1789 until his death in Claverack, New York on December 3, 1807.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Blachley Webb Papers consist of letterbooks, correspondence, journals, notebooks, orderly books, papers, and military records documenting the personal life and military career of Samuel Blachley Webb, who served in the American Revolutionary forces under Israel Putnam and George Washington. Notable correspondents include Joseph Barrell, Silas Deane Nathanael Otis, Timothy Pickering, Jonathan Trumbull, George Washington, and Catharine Hogeboom Webb.
SERIES I, LETTERBOOKS, 1764-1807, consists of two sections: General and Webb, Catharine Hogeboom. General contains nine volumes of correspondence and papers relating to Samuel Webb, his family, military and mercantile career from 1764-1807. Volumes one through eight are arranged in chronological order (boxes 1-8). Volume nine (box nine) contains material spanning the years 1773-90. Webb, Catharine Hogeboom contains two volumes (boxes 10-11) of correspondence Webb and his second wife exchanged from 1787-1801.
SERIES II, CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1756-1819, is arranged in two sections: General and Barrell, Joseph. General (box 12) consists of letters written to Webb, as well as his copies of selected outgoing correspondence. Barrell, Joseph (box 13) consists of correspondence and papers from Joseph Barrell to Samuel B. Webb, 1778-1801.
SERIES III, JOURNALS, NOTEBOOKS, AND MISCELLANEA, 175T-1805, is arranged in three sections: Webb, Samuel Blachley; Leslie, Alexander; and Lyman, Phineas. Webb, Samuel Blachley consists of a diary, journals and notebooks dating from 1775-1803. Diaries include the printed text for Stoddardfs Diary (The Columbia ALMANACK) from 1796-1803 and Webb's personal entries for scattered periods throughout these same years. Descriptions of family life, including the untimely death of his eldest daughter, and his local participation in the presidential election of 1802 are included.
A journal (1776-77) maintained by Webb from March 1, 1776 to December, 1777 describes his military actions and that of the American Revolutionary forces during this period, and includes information on British troop activities. A journal of orders, June 21, 1776 - August 8, 1776, contains a detailed recording of military orders, practices, and observations while Webb was in the service of General George Washington. Notebooks :for the years 1775-1807 generally detail the personal expenses Webb incurred.
Leslie, Alexander contains an orderly book of the British army captured at some point in 1776, and apparently the property of Brigadier General Alexander Leslie.
Lyman, Phineas contains an order book of this Major General and Colonel of "the troops raised by the Colony of Connecticut to act in conjunction with his Majesty's Regular Troops, under the command of his Excellency the Earl of Londoun."
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Letterbooks, 1764-1807. II. Correspondence and Papers, 1756-1819. III. Journals, Notebooks, and Miscellanea, 1757-1805.
Appendix: List of Correspondents
Alexander, William (Lord Stirling), 1726-1783
Alsop, John, 1730-1794
Ames,Fisher, 1758-1808
Axtell, Willam, 1720-1795
Babcock,Henry, 1736-1800
Bache,Theopylact, 1734-1807
Bancker, Sarah, 1731-1785
Barrell, Joseph, 1740-1804
Bard, Dr. Samuel, 1742-1821
Baylor, George 1752-1784
Bayard, James lsheton, 1767-1815
Bayard, Nicholas, 1736-1802
Beatty, John, 1749-1826
Beekman, John, 1720-1774
Beers, Nathan, 1753-1849
Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
Broome, John, 1738-1810
Bulfinch, Dr. Thomas, 1728-1802
Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836
Campbell, Sir Archibald, 1739-1791
Charlton, John 1736-1806
Chenevard, John, 1733-1805
Clarkson, Matthew. 1759-1S25
Clinton, Gov. George, 1739-1812
Cochran, Dr, John, 1730-1807
Cogsvell, Thomas, 1740-1810
Constable, William, 1752-1803
Crevecoeur, Michel Guillaume St. Jean de,
Dalton, Tristran, 1738-1817
Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
Dering, Sylvester, 1758-1820
Dexter, John Singer, 1764-1844
Duane, James, 1733-1797
Duert William, 1747-1799
Durkee, John, 1728-1782
Duyckinck, James, 1741-1822
Duyckinck, John, 1734-1812
Fish, Nicholas, 1758-1833
Flint, Royal, 1754-1797
Freeman, Jonathan, 1745-1808
Caine, Hugh, 1726-1807
Gates, Gen. Horatio, 1728-1806
Goodrich, Elihu Chauncey, 1764-1802
Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786
Griffin, Cyrus, 1748-1810
Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804
Hand, Edward, 1744-1802
Harrison, Richard, 1760-1841
Harrison, Robert Hanson, 1745-1790
Hazen, Moses, 1733-1802
Heath, William, 1737-1814
Hindman, William, 1743-1822
Hodgden, Samuel d.1824
Hogeboom Stephen, 1744-1814
Hosmer, Hezekiah Lord, 1765-1814
Hosmer, Titus, 1736-1780
Houstoun, Jolm, 1744-1796
Howe, Major Gen. Robert, d.1785
Hubbard, Nehemiah, 1732-1837
Hwnphreys, David, 1752-1818
Huntington, Ebenezer, 1754-1834
Huntington, Jedidiah, 1743-1818
Imley, William, 1743-1807
Izard, Henry, 1771-1826
Jackson, Henry, 1747-1809
Jackson, James, 1757-1806
Jay, Mary, 1736-1824
Keen, John, 1756-1795
Keese, John, 1755-1809
King, Rufus, 1755-1827
Lee, Henry, 1756-1818
L'Enfant, Peter Charles, 1755-1825
leonard, Rev. Abiel, 1740-1778
Leslie, Alexander, 1740-1794
Livingston, Catharine Ridley, 1751-1813
Livingston, Edward, 1764-1836
Livingston, Henry, 1752-1823
Livingston, Henry Brockholst, 1757-1823
Livingston, Henry Walter, 1768-1810
Livingston, John R., 1755-1851
Livingston, Philip, 1740-1810
Livingston,Philip, 1741-1787
Livingston, Chancellor Robert R., 1746-1813
Livingston, Walter, 1740-1797
Livingston, Gov. William, 1723-1790
Livingston, William, Jr., 1754-1817
Livingston, William Smith, 1755-1790
Loudon, Samuel, 1727-1813
Loring, Joshua, 1737-1789
Ludlow, Daniel, 1750-1814
McDougall, Alexander, 1731-1786
McEvers, Charles, 1739-1809
Middleton, Henry, 1770-1846
Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800
Moore, Benjamin, 1748-1816
Morris, Jacob, 1755-1844
Morris, Lewis, Jr., 1750-1824
Morris, lewis Richard, 1760-1825
Morris, Richard, 1730-1810
Moustier, Eleonore Francois Elie, marquis de, 1751-1817
Mumford, Thomas, 1728-1779
Murray, Lindley, 1745-1826
Olcott, George, 1751-1841
Otis, Samuel Alleyne, 1740-1814
Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789
Philipse, Frederick, 1746-1785
Phillips, William, 1731-1781
Pickering Timothy, 1745-1829
Pinckney, Charles, 1758-1824
Pintard, Lewis, 1732-1818
Platt, Hiehard, 1764-1832
Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785
Remsen, Henry, 1736-1792
Roosevelt, Isaac, 1726-1794
Sands, Cornelia (Lott), 1761-1856
Sage, Comfort, 1731-1799
Sargent, Winthrop, 1753-1820
Sehuyler, Philip Jeremias, 1768-1835
Schuyler, Philip -John, 1733-1804
Sears, Isaac, 1729-1786
Simpson, John, 1730-1777
Sitgreaves, John, 1740-1802
Skinner, Abraham, 1750-1825
Smith, Janet, 1730-1819
Smith, Thoms, 1745-1809
Smith, William, 1728-1793
Smith, William Stephens, 1755-1816
Splight, Richard obbs, 1758-1802
Spencer, Ambrose, 1765-1848
Steuben, Frederick William Augustus Henry Ferdinand von, 1730-1794
Stevens, John, 1749-1838
Stewart, Col. Walter, 1756-1796
Sullivan, James, 1744-1808
Suillvan, John, 1740-1795
Swan, James, 1754-1881
Swift, Heman, 1733-1814
Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835
Temple, Sir John, 1732-1798
Tilghnnn, Tench, 1744-1786
Thomas, David, 1762-1831
Thompson, William, 1725-1781
Trumbull, John, 1756-1843
Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785
Trumbull, Jonathan, 1740-1809
Tudor, Elihu, 1732-1826
Van Cortlandt, Augustus, b.1728
Varnum, James Mitchell, 1748-1789
Verplanck, Guilan, 1750-1799
Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1743-1804
Walker, Robert, 1745-1810
Walton, Gerard, 1741-1821
Waddington, Joshua, 1755-1844
Walton, William, 1731-1796
Washington, George, 1732-1799
Washington, Martha Curtis, 1732-1802
Watson, James, 1750-1806
Watts, John, 1749-1836
Webb, Catherine Hogeboom, 1765-1805
Webb, Joseph, 1700-1791
Webb, Mehitabel, 1757-1796
Wignall, Thomas, 1753-1803
Williams, Otho Holland, 1749-1794
Williams, Samuel William, 1752-1812
Wimple, Walter Vrooman, 1751-1798
Winslow, John, 1753-1819
Husband and wife; New York (State) -- Economic conditions; Peekskill (N.Y.) -- History; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Account books; Diaries; Merchants; Soldiers; Ames, Fisher, 1758-1808; Barrell, Joseph, 1739-1804; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Heath, William, 1737-1814; Livingston, Brockholst, 1757-1823; Livingston, Edward, 1764-1836; McDougall, Alexander, 1732-1786; Morris, Lewis, 1754-1824; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; Pinckney, Charles, 1757-1824; Pintard, Lewis, 1732-1818; Spencer, Ambrose, 1765-1848; Steuben, Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, Baron von, 1730-1794; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785; Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1743-1804; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Webb, Samuel Blachley, 1753-1807
- LETTERBOOKS, 1764-1807; Series I; 6
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains bound volumes of original letters arranged in two sections: General and Webb, Catharine Hogeboom.
  General is arranged in chronological order, with the exception of volume 9, which contains material spanning the years 1733-90.
  Webb, Catharine Hogeboom is arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - 1764-1777 (Box 1)
      General note
      See also: Box 9, Folder 1
    - 1778 (Box 2)
    - 1779 (Box 3)
    - 1780-1781 (Box 4)
    - 1782-1783 (Box 5)
    - 1784-1786 (Box 6)
    - 1787-1789 (Box 7)
    - 1790-1807 (Box 8)
    - 1773-1790 (Box 9)
  - Webb, Catharine Hogeboom
    - 1787-1789 (Box 10)
    - 1790-1801 (Box 11)
- CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1756-1819; Series II; 0.75
  This series is arranged in two sections: General and Barrell, Joseph. Each is arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - 1756-1819, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-34)
    - Letter signed to Samuel B, Webb from George Washington, 1782 November 11 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Wasington, generalissime des États unis de l'Amérique [graphic] / dessiné par Bounieu; d'après un tableau fourni par M.le Marquis de la Fayette; gravé par Chevillet, circa 1800 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Portrait engraving of George Washington. Washington's name is misspelled.
  - Barrell, Joseph, 1778-1801, undated (Box 13, Folder 35-41)
- JOURNALS, NOTEBOOKS, AND MISCELLANEA, 1757-1807; Series III; 0.25
  This series is arranged in three sections: Webb, Samuel Blachley; Leslie, Alexander; and Lyman, Phineas. Each is arranged alphabetically by the type of material.
  - Webb, Samuel Blachley
    - Diary, 1796-1803 (Box 14, Folder 42-43)
    - Journal, 1776-77 (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - Journal of orders, 1776 June 21-August 8 (Box 14, Folder 45)
    - Notebooks, 1775-1807 (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - Leslie, Alexander, orderly book, 1776 (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Lyman, Phineas, orders, 1757 (Box 14, Folder 48)